Okay, so in this video, we're going to
discuss the development life cycles.
Now, there are four basic development life
cycles, right, that you
need to be aware of.
You've got the predictive life cycle,
you've got the iterative life cycle,
incremental, and then agile.
And there's actually
also a fifth one called the
hybrid, right, which I'll
talk about in just a second.
However, let's talk about each of these
four first, right?
So, predictive first.
Now, the predictive life cycle,
predictive project is your traditional.
project management
or the traditional project
that, you know, we
always hear about, right?
The traditional waterfall type of life
cycle where you get your requirements from
the customer at the
beginning of the project, right,
and then you deliver
at the end of the project.
You deliver one time
at the end of the project,
and then there's many
different phases in between.
You finish one phase,
then you start the next
phase, and then you
start the next phase, right?
So kind of like the waterfall methodology,
as I just mentioned.
That's your predictive.
So, for example, construction projects.
Construction projects are generally going
to be predictive.
When you're building a house, you get the
requirements at the
beginning of the project.
You've got the design of the house and all
the requirements of the house.
And then the builder is going to be
building the house and you're going to
deliver the product the one time at the
end of the project.
At the other end of the scale,
you have an agile project.
And an Agile project, then, you are
incrementally delivering your product to
the customer or
incrementally delivering value
to the customer, right,
every couple of weeks.
So in an agile project, an iteration is
known as a sprint.
So each iteration, you're
going to be delivering something,
and each sprint is generally
going to be two to four weeks.
It doesn't have to be, but
purpose of the PMP exam
generally assume it's going
to be two to four weeks.
So in an Agile, then, you're constantly
involving the customer, right,
and you're constantly delivering every
couple of weeks.
You're constantly delivering something to
the customer, something of value.
Right.
So you're getting your requirements
throughout.
The requirements can change.
So Agile allows for a constantly changing
business environment.
It allows for a constant change as
requirements are changing.
Then what you are
delivering is going to be
changing throughout,
throughout an Agile project.
Now, in between then, you
have what's known as the
iterative and the
incremental life cycles as well.
With the iterative life cycle,
you are essentially delivering the product
the one time, delivering the product to
the customer the one time, right,
where and you get your
requirements, but then
there may be several
iterations of the same phase.
So it's almost like saying,
right, you're going to
take a stab at this, say,
developing this system first.
We're going to take a stab at it.
And then we're going to
make some successive
refinements, right, until
we get the final product.
So as a simple example, right,
so, you know, using my personal
background, right, so my personal HR
background.
So let's say we're implementing a HR
system.
We're implementing a HR system for a
Fortune 100 client, So it's a big client.
They've got many, many employees.
And we're delivering the entire HR suite,
which is going to include the payroll
system, the benefit system, equity
compensation, the 401k defined
contribution, health insurance and life
insurance, and so and so forth.
It's just a couple of things that I've
mentioned, a few things I've mentioned.
But let's say we're delivering the entire
HR suite.
Now, a typical organization, a large
organization is going to have many,
many, types of employees right and
employees are all going to have different
types of benefits and different payroll
deductions and and so on and so forth
right based on whether the part-time
whether the full-time right whether
they're a trade union worker a non-trade
union worker right there's location
specific benefits right there's a
different benefits based on whether
they're at management level or you know
general worker level whether they're a
blue-collar worker or white-collar worker
and so on and so forth I'm so what we what
we're going to do is, right, we,
so in an iterative then, right,
we've got many iterations of the same,
you know, of the same phase, right?
So as we're identifying all
of these different populations,
right, then we're going to be
doing more and more work.
We're going to be doing more tests as we
identify more populations
and so on and so forth.
So we will create the basic system,
right?
We'll create the basic system and then
we'll make successive refinements to the
system as more and more
populations of employees are
discovered, but there'll
be one delivery at the end.
Whereas with incremental, in the same
example, we will make different,
rather, we will deliver the product at
various points.
We're not just going to have one delivery
at the end.
We will first, for example, deliver the
payroll system, then we'll deliver the
benefit system, then we'll
deliver 401K, you know, defined
contribution 401K system,
right, and so and so forth.
So we're going to be delivering value,
you know, at various points.
Now, that sounds very much like Agile,
but the basic difference is.
I mean, the biggest difference is that
Agile is very quick, very, very quick
succession, right, where with incremental,
each iteration might be several months.
In Agile, an iteration is going to be two
to four weeks in incremental.
mental, it could be several months.
Now, just some characteristics then.
Let's go through each of
these characteristics, right,
and compare it to these
different types of life cycles.
So requirements, in a predictive
environment, requirement is fixed.
Right, you're delivering one fixed item at
the end of the project.
So, for example, when
you're building a house, right,
you're delivering that house
at the end of the project.
So you're not going to first deliver the
kitchen and then deliver the dining room
and then deliver the master bedroom,
right?
You're not going to be delivering,
you know, rooms at a time.
You have to deliver the whole house,
right?
So requirements then are basically going
to be fixed.
So it's a single delivery, right?
Single delivery and requirements are
fixed.
You get the requirements
from the customer at the
beginning and then you
deliver it at the end, right?
The fixed requirements, that any changes
then are going to be expensive.
Right.
So, you know, you don't make too many
changes.
So with predictive, then, change control
is absolutely vital.
Any changes, you know, it's going to be
expensive.
You have to go through a proper change
control process.
Now, in an iterative environment,
then, again, it's one single delivery at
the end, right, but the requirements can
change.
And in fact, with
iterative, incremental, and
agile, it allows for
changing requirements.
Requirements can change as more
information is gathered.
But in an iterative, it's still going to
be one single delivery at the end.
We've got many iterations of the same
phase, whereas with incremental,
it's going to be the incremental
life cycle, you're going
to have more frequent
delivery of the product or value.
And agile is even more frequent delivery.
In agile, it's going to be every couple of
weeks.
In incremental, it could be several
months.
So change then with predictive is going to
be very very controlled, as I mentioned.
In Agile, it's a complete other end of the
spectrum, where it incorporates change.
As things are changing, requirements can
change.
It allows for external
changing business environment,
or things could be
changing internally, right?
And so requirements can change.
It allows for change.
And with iterative and incremental,
it also allows for change, but change is
going to be incorporated
at various points,
right, along each iteration
along each increment.
Stakeholder involvement then.
In a predictive, stakeholders are not
involved as much, right, key stakeholders.
You're involved at the beginning,
a lot to give the requirements,
right, and then maybe
at various points, various
milestones, they'll be there to sign off.
But in between, there's not a lot of
involvement.
With Agile, it's continuous involvement.
You're delivering something every couple
of weeks, and as requirements are
changing, or rather as
a business environment
is changing, the requirements can change.
And so the customer is constantly involved
in an agile environment.
In an iterative increment, iterative or
incremental, regular involvement,
again, generally at the beginning and end
of each iteration or each increment,
or that's where they'll have the most
amount of involvement.
But then because iterations and increments
could be, you know, weeks or months,
right, instead of, say, you know,
beginning, an end of a project in a
predictive, there's still more involvement
than you would have in a predictive.
And then how often is the work performed?
Well, in a predictive environment,
you generally perform the work once.
Obviously, you know, you
test the work and so and so
forth, but you generally
perform the work once, right?
You don't repeat the work over and over
again until you get it right.
So, for example, again, building a house,
right?
You don't, you're not going
to do the plumbing and then
test it again and then do it
again and then keep doing.
No, you do the plumbing the one time.
You do the electrical the one time.
You don't keep successively updating the
pipes and updating the electrical system.
No, you just do it the one time.
Whereas iterative and incremental,
it's repeated.
And agile, again, continuously repeated.
So when are they best suited?
For a predictive environment,
right, it's well generally,
predictive will be when it's
a well-understood project.
We know what the outcome is.
So again, building a house.
We know what the final product is.
We know what's all the tasks that need to
be done in between.
Predictive is going to work well there.
Is Agile going to work well in a
construction environment?
No, because Agile works in a continuously
changing business environment.
So software development, cell phones,
cell phone apps.
It's a constantly, constantly changing
business environment.
Right.
So things are constantly changing.
So your requirements need to constantly be
updated.
Your requirements need to constantly
change.
That's where Agile is going to work the
best.
Right.
Agile is not going to work in every single
industry, in every situation.
Right.
So construction, Agile doesn't work very
well in construction.
Right.
Agile is not going to work very well.
For example, if you're creating a new
airline, right, or a cruise ship,
for example, right?
Because, you know, it's not.
a constantly changing environment,
right?
However, you have iterative and
incremental, iterative, where the scope is
determined early, but, you know,
we know we need to make modifications in
between and incremental, right,
where we need to deliver items,
right, but at successive increments.
So, like the example I just gave you
earlier.
Now, there's also another one called the
hybrid life cycle.
And the hybrid, specifically,
whenever you come across this
for the exam is a combination
between predictive and agile.
Now, many organizations, they want to,
you know, they like the idea of agile,
right, in many industries,
agile, they like the idea
of agile, but a pure agile
environment might not work.
And so they have a mixture, right, they
have a hybrid of predictive and agile.
So they may have several iterations,
for example, or rather they may have
phases, and then within
each phase, right, you
have a mixture, you
have an agile approach.
Now, any organization, though, doesn't
have to be one or the other, right?
And typically, many organizations have a
mixture of any of these types of life
cycles, any of these types of
methodologies.
You can have a mixture of methodologies.
For example, you have scrum and can ban,
collectively they're known a scrum ban,
right?
There's many different types of hybrid
methodology that you could be using.
So remember for the exam, the exam is 50%
predictive and 50% agile and hybrid.
Now, just to summarize what we just said
here on this next slide, right?
So is this shown what I said in a
graphical form?
On the y-axis, you've got frequency of
delivery.
In the x, you've got degree of change,
right?
So if there's high frequency
of delivery and high degree
of change, agile would be
best suited in that situation.
You've got low frequency of delivery,
right?
You're delivering it once.
and low degree of change, there's not
going to be a huge amount of change,
but changes are going
to be expensive, then
predictive environment
will be well suited for that.
If you have low delivery, right,
so low frequency delivery again,
you're delivering it the
one time, but there's
going to be generally
high degree of change.
It can be making changes over and over
again.
That would be iterative, but then high
frequency of delivery, such as you're
going to be delivering one product,
then another, then another, then another,
then another, but within each increment,
degree of change is going to be low,
right, then that would be incremental.
Incremental would be best suited for that.
All right, so these were the development
life cycles.
Again, remember, the question is generally
50% is going to be predictive,
50% agile and hybrid.